It is no surprise to me,
that these Northmen
have arrived in Wessex.
After I heard about their
raids into Northumbria,
I realized it was only
a matter of time,
before they came ashore here.
When I lived at the court
of the Emperor Charlemagne,
of long and blessed memory,
these Northmen had already
emerged, from their lairs,
to attack parts of his empire.
And I remember an incident,
from this period very well.
I was with Charlemagne's party,
at a harbor town,
in southern Gaul.
As we sat eating supper,
a fleet of pirates
attacked the harbor.
There was some confusion
about their identity,
but from the build
of their ships, and their
speed through the water,
the Emperor recognized them
at once as Northmen.
After a lightning attack...
They made their escape.
The Emperor's men
took up the chase,
but, they were soon out-sailed.
Charlemagne, rose
from the table, and stood
at the window, facing east.
I remember it as clearly,
as if it were yesterday.
For a long time he stood,
while the tears,
poured down his face.
In the end, he said,
Do you know why
I weep so bitterly?
It's not because I'm afraid,
these ruffians
will do me any harm.
I am sick at heart
to think, that
even in my lifetime,
they have dared
to attack this coast.
And I am horror-stricken,
when I foresee,
what evil they will do,
to my descendants
and their subjects.
And now, it is our turn,
to deal with these ruffians.
These pagans.
But deal with them we shall.
And must.
Aethelwulf?
Yes, Father.
I put it in your hands,
to work with our ealdormen,
to raise an army.
In the meantime,
we shall send spies and others,
to observe the size
of the raiding party,
and their intentions.
These Northmen
never like to venture
far from their ships,
and they prefer not to be
drawn into pitched battle.
Let us not be afraid,
but rather watchful.
And ultimately, decisive.
As the Emperor was.
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
What is that place?
It's a Christian church,
a minster.
A large one.
It may be Winchester.
Is it important?
If it is Winchester,
Saint Birinus is
buried there.
It's a place of
great pilgrimage.
And will there
be treasure there?
Yes. A lot
of treasure.
(CHUCKLES)
(EAGLE SCREECHES)
SIGVARD: Lagertha!
Why must I follow
you up the fields?
You're my wife.
You should be at my side,
especially when we
have important guests.
I will not stay to
hear my son insulted.
Your son should
know his place.
He continues
to be resentful.
He refuses to
accept or acknowledge
my love for him.
You don't
love my son.
You don't love
anyone, Sigvard.
You don't know how to.
(GROANS)
Forgive me, Lagertha.
I'm an intemperate man.
I find it difficult
to control myself.
But I have loved
and desired you
after my fashion,
and if your son will
only meet me halfway,
I will make sure he
has a good future.
(SHEEP BLEATING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
(SHUDDERING)
(BELL TOLLING)
MAN 1: The alarm!
(CLAMORING)
MAN 2: Inside, now!
(BELL CONTINUES TOLLING)
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
(GROANS)
(CROWD SCREAMING)
Ready?
Weapons!
(BELL CONTINUES TOLLING)
(ANIMALS BLEATING)
(SHOUTING)
(SHOUTS)
(GRUNTS)
(MAN SCREAMS)
(SHOUTS)
(SCREAMS)
(GRUNTING)
(PANTING)
(GRUNTS)
(SCREAMING)
Could be a trap.
Shield-wall!
Open.
Where have
they all gone?
There should
be treasure.
He said there
would be treasure.
Why do you always
listen to him?
Where is it?
It's over there.
This? This is
not treasure.
This is an empty
wooden table.
You are mistaken,
King Horik.
The treasure is here.
You're standing on it.
(KNOCKS)
(STRAINING)
(GRUNTING)
(LAUGHS)
You were right!
(MEN LAUGHING)
Look, it's treasure!
How did you know?
It is a Christian habit,
to bury the bones,
of the revered dead,
beneath the altar.
Ragnar!
HORIK: Let me see that.
(TREASURE CLATTERING)
(MEN LAUGHING)
Who was this?
It must be
Saint Birinus.
You keep talking to me
like I know what
a saint is.
A saint is a man
who has lived a
particularly holy life,
performed some miracle,
or been martyred,
killed, for their beliefs.
MAN: It's all gold!
But I am dead.
What use can I be?
(CHUCKLES)
Christians
believe that the bones,
can still exert benediction.
Can perform miracles.
What is a miracle?
Miracles are things
which are impossible to do.
HORIK: Take it all.
It's heavy.
Wait.
MAN: What do they want?
(WOMAN GASPS)
(WOMAN SCREAMS)
(SHUDDERING)
No! Stop!
(GROANS)
(GASPING)
(SPEAKING
IN NATIVE TONGUE)
(ATHELSTAN SPEAKING
Hide!
You speak
our language. How?
It doesn't matter.
Just do as I say. Hide.
Hide, or they
will kill you.
You're one of us.
Once.
Then, I will
tell you this.
One day,
you will be caught.
We will catch you
and crucify you,
for an apostate is the
lowest, and the vilest,
of all creatures,
in the eyes of God.
Oh.
(IN NATIVE TONGUE)
He's coming with us.
(SCREAMING)
(IN NATIVE TONGUE)
Here is their main priest.
You preach against our gods.
You say there is only one God,
but you are a liar
and an old fool.
The gods hate you,
but I hate you even more.
(SPEAKING LATIN)
(GROANS)
(MEN LAUGHING)
(IN NATIVE TONGUE)
Tie him up.
Let us have some fun with him.
(CHEERING)
What will
happen to him?
You just wait
and see, Priest.
(MEN LAUGH)
(PRIEST PRAYING IN LATIN)
(GROANS)
(MEN CHEER)
(CONTINUES PRAYING)
(RUSTLING)
(OBJECTS CLATTERING)
(MAN CHEERS)
MAN: More treasure!
Here!
(GROANS)
(MEN CHEERING)
(LAUGHING)
(PRIEST PRAYING IN LATIN)
(MEN CHEER)
(CONTINUES PRAYING)
FLOKI: Is he still talking?
Tough old goat.
HORIK: Erlendur, quiet him.
Right in his mouth.
(GASPING)
(PRIEST CONTINUES PRAYING)
(GASPS)
(BLESSING IN LATIN)
Suffer no more,
but trust in
thy salvation.
(GROANS WEAKLY)
(SLICES)
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
Mother,
why would you allow him
to do that to you?
What are you
talking about?
Your husband,
Earl Sigvard.
I saw him.
Bjorn, please.
Please what?
Has he
hit you before?
Will you let
him hit you again?
It will never
happen again.
If it does,
I'll kill him.
I said it won't.
What would
Ragnar say?
What has it to do
with your father?
Nothing.
Sometimes I think
of him.
I miss him.
I can't help it.
Of course not.
You're his son.
You must
always be proud.
As should you,
for being his wife.
(CHILDREN PLAYING)
(SIGHS)
Another son?
(BABY COOS)
Yes.
What is his name?
Sigurd,
after my father.
Sigurd Snake-in-the-Eye.
MAN: Close the gate!
EDMUND:
Your Majesty, you have heard
of the attack on Winchester?
Of course.
I grieve.
EDMUND: The martyrdom of
my fellow bishop,
Bishop Swithern.
A fine Christian.
ECBERT: Praise be to God.
There are those who ask,
why we did not do more,
to protect our
brothers and sisters,
at such an important site.
ECBERT: Are there?
What answer did you give them,
My Lord Eadric?
Perhaps he did not
have an answer.
I've never found Lord Eadric
to be at a loss for words.
(MEN LAUGH)
I confess, that
in this case, it's true.
I had no ready answer.
No, because it's always easier
to be wise, after the fact,
is it not?
My kingdom is very large.
There are many
important sites.
Could I protect
all of them? No.
Did I want to discover
where the pagans
would strike?
Yes.
For now I know
where they are.
So Bishop Swithern
was a necessary
sacrifice.
As a man of God,
I assumed he welcomed
the opportunity for martyrdom.
Or do you disagree?
Oh, no, Sire.
All of the cloth,
would welcome martyrdom,
in the cause of our faith,
service of our
lord Jesus Christ.
Good.
Because I'm going to
offer you, precisely
that same opportunity,
My Lord Bishop.
And, I trust,
very soon.
(SIGHS DEEPLY)
TORSTEIN: It's times like this
I miss our friend Arne.
He could always make us laugh.
Even in the darkest moments.
Now, he's making
the gods laugh.
That's why they
took him from us,
'cause they were jealous.
(CHUCKLES)
Speaking of gods...
I have something
for you, Athelstan.
Don't you want it?
Are these not
the images of your god?
I told you before,
and I will tell you again.
My god is Odin,
the Allfather.
I know you've told me.
Only, I don't believe you.
And this?
Ragnar gave me this.
Wearing a dog turd
doesn't make you a dog.
Oh!
I have something
else for you.
The hand of your
holy man, I believe.
(CHUCKLES)
So tell me,
how do you
find England?
It is a pleasant land,
rich with treasure.
You are right.
This land is rich.
But here,
here is the
real treasure.
(SMELLS)
Earth?
Have you not seen?
Everywhere we go,
there are crops.
There is food growing.
I am a farmer and
the son of a farmer,
and this is what
I understand.
Compared to
our poor countries
where it is hard to farm,
hard to live,
here, it is easy.
If we lived here,
we could feed everybody.
There would be no hunger.
I like your thinking,
but here is my question.
Will the Saxons
simply invite us
to live among them?
Hmm?
(PEOPLE CHEERING LOUDLY)
(APPLAUDING)
(CHEERING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
Friends, family,
what's left of it,
so, I am married
for the second time.
As most of you know,
my first marriage
lasted less than an hour,
because my own brother
poisoned the drinks that day.
Of course, the same thing
can never happen twice,
so let the wine
be poured.
(CHEERING)
(BANGING TABLE)
Now, who will be the first
to drink in celebration?
I will.
No. No,
I could not bear it.
Not a second time.
Let me taste the wine.
(COUGHING)
That's good enough.
(CHEERING)
I have something
else important to say.
I don't wish to
dampen the celebrations,
but you all know
that the agreement
between myself,
King Horik and
Ragnar Lothbrok
has been broken.
They have
gone raiding west
without me, without us,
which is an insult
not only to myself,
but to all of you.
And now, also to my wife
and to my wife's family.
I have to do
something about
this insult.
Frankly, I blame
King Horik more
for what has happened,
but at the same time, consider
what is happening to
Earl Ragnar's lands.
He has abandoned them,
to the care of his wife,
and his drunken brother.
(LAUGHING)
In order to punish those,
who have insulted
me and my family,
I declare today, that
I will seek vengeance,
against Ragnar Lothbrok.
By all our gods,
I swear, that we will
seize, all his lands,
and that I will repay,
his brother's
treachery, with the ax.
(CHEERING)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
Who can speak to us?
I can.
I have been sent
here by Ecbert,
King of Wessex.
The King regrets
your attack, on the
holy church at Winchester.
He wonders how much
longer, you intend to
remain in his kingdom.
(CLEARS THROAT)
Well, that depends.
EDMUND: Upon what?
Upon what he'll
offer us to leave.
Or what he'll
offer us to stay.
Stay?
Yes, we want to make
peace with the King.
Peace.
(GROANS)
(MEN LAUGH)
So we don't have to
kill any more of you.
I will relay your
message to the King.
(FLOKI CHUCKLES)
(SPEAKING IN NATIVE TONGUE)
(GROANS)
(LAUGHS)
(GRUNTING)
(STRAINING)
(MEN LAUGHING)
(GROANS)
(LAUGHING)
(NEIGHS)
SIGVARD: Not hungry, Bjorn?
No.
Any reason?
No reason.
Are you unhappy?
What can I do to
make you happy?
Shall I
raid one of my
unsuspecting neighbors,
so you can show off
your fighting skills?
And maybe slaughter
them all?
Show that you are
truly the son of
Ragnar Lothbrok?
(MEN LAUGHING)
SIGVARD:
No, believe me,
I do not like to
see you so solemn.
So tell me,
what can I do?
You can let me go
live in a cabin
in the mountains.
By yourself?
In the mountains?
Yes.
I'd like to test myself.
Get away from all this.
All these servants.
All these people
doing everything for us.
I want to know what
is essential to life.
What is
really important.
Will you let me?
No. Of course not.
I am the earl here.
What would folk
think, if I let my
beloved stepson starve
or freeze to death,
in some mountain pigsty?
(MEN LAUGH)
SIGVARD:
You understand that,
don't you, my boy?
In any case,
I have solemnly sworn
to Lagertha, that I
shall take care of you.
And I will.
Rollo!
Rollo, wake up.
What?
What is it?
There are boats.
SIGGY: Who are they?
ROLLO:
I think I can guess.
Go back to the town.
Find anyone
who can fight.
Anyone who can
hold a weapon.
We're under attack.
Rollo, what is it?
What is happening?
Jarl Borg.
He has come
back to attack us.
Jarl Borg?
I'm sure
it is him.
Ragnar and King Horik
broke their
agreement with him.
He has returned to
gain his revenge.
What are we
going to do?
What do you think
we're going to do?
We're going to fight.
Come. Go! Go!
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
ROLLO: Torfin! Olaf!
One of you on each flank.
Help with the barricades.
Ragnar has taken
all of the best
fighting men.
Look what we have left.
What are you doing?
What does it look like?
Not you.
You are not
a shield-maiden.
You're not...
Lagertha.
Siggy, I need
you to go back
to the Great Hall.
Find Princess Aslaug
and her children,
and take them up
into the mountains.
And then what?
Wait.
For what?
For whatever
the gods have decided
is about to happen.
Now go.
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
Come on.
This way.
To the mountains.
Go, Hvitserk.
Run. Quickly.
Sail down!
(HORN BLOWS)
Row! Row!
ROLLO: Stay strong!
Don't make it
easy for them!
Light the fires!
(MEN SHOUTING)
(BANGING)
ROLLO: Archers!
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
Oars!
ROLLO: Hold your places!
Jump ship!
(SHOUTS)
Go!
(SHOUTING)
(GROANS)
(GRUNTING)
(SCREAMS)
(GROANS)
As fast as you can!
Shields!
BOY: Rollo!
Fall back!
(SHOUTS)
Back to the
marketplace.
Move!
That's right,
Rollo, run!
Run, like
you always do.
(SHOUTING)
(GRUNTS)
Loose!
Shield-wall!
You can't win,
Rollo!
There is no disgrace,
in the eyes of the gods,
to save yourself
for another day.
(GROANS)
(GASPING)
Your first duty
is to try and save
the sons of Ragnar.
Surrender!
Rollo,
let me speak for the gods,
for I will shortly join them
in their bright halls.
But you, you have
other work to do here.
Go.
I will tell the gods
what you have done.
Now do you surrender?
(SHOUTS)
(SCREAMS)
(ALL SHOUTING)
(LAUGHING)